<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Schreck&#39;s cross-country ski news</title>
  <subtitle>News from the waxing bench</subtitle>
  <link href="https://schreckski.com/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://schreckski.com/" />
  <updated>2025-05-05T16:29:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://schreckski.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Schreck</name>
    <email>schreckski@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Where can we ski next season and the pluses and minuses?</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2025/05/where-can-we-ski/" />
    <updated>2025-05-05T16:29:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2025/05/where-can-we-ski/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;HI Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, it&#39;s May and the last thing you&#39;re probably interested in is XC skiing. Golf and gardening are on your mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I had a question and thought you might store this so I won&#39;t have to answer the question ever again!:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey Schreck, Where can I Cross Country ski?????&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s a quick comparison of the places folks in the Seattle metropolitan area can XC ski and the typical season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of us XC skiers in King, Pierce, Kittitas and surrounding counties, we are very lucky to XC ski so many places in the Snoqualmie Pass mountains. Groomed west to east in the corridor, we have the Summit, Hyak, Crystal Springs,  Cabin Creek,  Lake Easton and Suncadia Nordic ski areas.  Multiple groomers allow us many opportunities in the winter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I am skiing with my friends in May right now. I also skied last November.  Both times on perfect grooming.  Obviously I wasn&#39;t skiing in the Snoqualmie Pass Corridor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only downside to our Snoqualmie area XC ski season is that it&#39;s only about 12 to maybe 14 weeks if we&#39;re lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the earliest grooming can begin at our Washington SnoParks is in December.  And the latest, like the last several years,  is March 31st. That&#39;s just current policy for Washington state SnoPark system (and so it seems, for Boyne Resorts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This season, the first full grooming at a Washington SnoPark (and not counting some preliminary rolling) was late, on December 27th.  But I already had skied in November, snd lots in December, well before Christmas and some in April and now May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can too. You just need to travel in the Pacific Northwest. Here&#39;s how:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mid/Late November and into December: as soon as enough snow falls (the amount varies with equipment,) XC skiing begins at the Methow Valley, Silver Star, Mt. Bachelor and even Suncadia; why? Well, because they can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Silver Star, a high elevation, 4,000&#39;+ Alpine and XC resort in Northern B.C. is usually first.
Plus: you are skiing!
Minus: long flight, dark at 9 am and 3 pm. Very cold!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Near Bend, 6,400&#39; at the lodge, Mt. Bachelor Nordic Center is around Thanksgiving most years but as early as they can. I skied before Thanksgiving this year!
Plus: you can drive 6 hours. Bend is fun. Grooming is superb.
Minus: 6,000&#39;+ elevation.  Bring your strong lungs! It snows, blows, and is pretty cold most days in November and December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*The Methow Valley Ski area is the largest XC grooming in North America and has opened as early as late November.  They use snowmobiles and can groom as little as 6 inches.
Plus: it&#39;s got the most groomed trails so you&#39;ll never be bored.&lt;br&gt;
Minus: be prepared for cold Temps and gets dark earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Finally, it&#39;s rare but I have skied mid November two seasons ago at Suncadia on excellent classic grooming.  They have a normal and a small snowmobile grooming machine for 6 inches like the Methow.
Plus: it&#39;s free and you can ski with me!  No SnoPark or lift pass needed.
Minus: it&#39;s narrow so bring your classic skis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*After December 1st,  grooming can begin with rolling on Washington SnoPark trails at Cabin Creek, Hyak, and Crystal Springs SnoParks.  I have skied as early as December 2nd and began as late as, well, January 2nd on our SnoPark trails! Grooming is usually 6 days a week although we get some Tuesdays at Cabin mid winter. No grooming on Christmas or New Years day.  Trollhaugen trails are groomed usually Wednesday,  Saturday and Sunday.&lt;br&gt;
*Finally, Lake Easton is groomed when they get a couple feet, usually in January and February. Hard stop for all grooming on March 31st at all Washington Sno Parks.
Plus: $120/carload! Good groomers.  Screaming deal!
Minus: Porta potties and getting crowded on weekends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*Summit, owned by Boyne Resorts, mostly tries to open for the Christmas to New Years break. Friday to Sunday grooming until sometime in March.
Plus: Top is great.  Chair lift to it if it&#39;s open.
Minus: you can&#39;t ski with me (maybe a plus!) Expensive day/pass rate, and you also pay $55 daily to park if you don&#39;t buy an expensive pass. One trail to top, the Cold Creek road trail can be thin, dirty, crowded with snowshoes and all uphill to the top. They have lifts running, alpine skiers and snowboarding on the face which you can join.  Otherwise,  Hidden Valley is only way down.  It&#39;s a steep black diamond run down from top.  Can be walked. Great for expert skiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;April/May: So you can still classic or backcountry ski the P2C Trail and maybe Amabilis Mountain in the first week or two.
Minus: Not groomed and dirty snow. Snowmobiles are a menace. The Methow is usually thin to over by March 31st.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now is the time to go to Mt Bachelor! PLUS: They usually have the longest and best snow cover in North America.  Many years they groom up to the last weekend in May and 7 days a week! A Spring XC pass is $139 this year for April and May.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&#39;s why I am skiing currently at Mt. Bachelor.  Because I can! They have a 10 foot base!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember to wax on and leave on til Winter your wax if you&#39;re not skiing at Mt. BACHELOR!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My website is up Schreckski.com
January and February are open for reservations.  Weekends and Wednesdays are filling up fast. I want you, my returning XC skiing students and also your friends and families to have dibs on your favorite dates/times. You asked and I will add a calendar soon with my openings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SEE YOU SKIING SOON!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s gravel bike once we can&#39;t XC Ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thanks for a great XC ski season!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2025/04/thanks/" />
    <updated>2025-04-07T15:19:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2025/04/thanks/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank you for having faith in my teaching abilities and booking one to ten XC ski lessons with me this season, ages 4 to 84! I thought you&#39;d like a recap of this last Schreckski XC ski Season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I taught you and others like you, mostly privates, lots of couples, trios of friends, all day lessons at the Methow Valley Ski Camp and a birthday 🎂 party of 12 never evers how to ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In just 13 weeks, I taught 118 students (one but mostly four lessons) for a total of 226 lessons ( 75-minute to 2.5 hour sessions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While teaching, frantically racing to my next lesson or on the rare free ski day with my daughter or my friends,  I XC skated 60 days, classic skied 52 days for 528 skate miles and 429 Classic miles. Only 957 miles so no record this season.  But there&#39;s always next season!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to reserve a two-pack private tune-up lesson for next year or learn how to skate or Classic XC with a four-pack, my 2025/2026 website Schreckski.com is now only open for you, my returning students (ok and your close friends if you refer them).  I won&#39;t open it up to &amp;quot;new to me&amp;quot; students until October so you have first dibs on your favorite day to ski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love to teach skiing almost as much as I love to free ski with my daughter and friends.  I will be teaching less and free skiing more next season. So I want you to be able to get on my shorter schedule so I can free ski in December,  Tuesdays and Fridays.  My new schedule and daily slots are on my updated and open Website Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lessons are a half hour later due to the new grooming schedule.  All lessons are 75-minute on the website. If you, my returning students request a two hour, I will do it only for you in the last session of the day BUT don&#39;t let others know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start times
8:30
10am
*11:30 reserved for you. *NOT on website Also the time slot for two hour lessons .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same locations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mondays at Hyak. With the new grooming in the teaching area, we have a quiet place with a nice hill to ski. Skate or Classic&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rest of lesson days are still at Crystal Springs SnoPark.  With two groomers, if one breaks, we still have a backup!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesdays and Sundays are intermediate to advanced skate lesson days at Crystal Springs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursdays and Saturdays are groomed best for intermediate to advanced Classic lessons at Crystal Springs SnoPark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No lessons in December this coming season.  I plan to follow the groomers every day and teach at the Methow Valley Ski Camp 🏕.  You can book January and February lessons any time, but the slots go to the first to Venmo my account which is on my website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you have an awesome summer.  Let me know if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For good skiers, I teach safe rollerskiing on smooth bike paths in Suncadia.  I also teach how to be safe and stop on rollerskis. I only offer this to my students.  Dates and times are flexible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you gravel bike, let me know when you&#39;re in the area and I can show you our sweet champagne gravel routes. I plan again on racing the 700 mile XWA, a gravel mtb bike race across the dirt of Washington in May. Then I&#39;m bikepacking the 500 mile Northern Blues and Wallawa Mountains gravel bike route in June. Probably be lazy lounging at the pool in July!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s gravel bike now that we can&#39;t XC Ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>March XC Ski Season and what to expect for the future in April</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2025/03/march-season/" />
    <updated>2025-03-23T16:05:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2025/03/march-season/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have 9 more groomed ski days before we have to travel to Mt. Bachelor Nordic Center to find grooming this season.  Washington XC ski grooming ends March 31st.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Summit at Snoqualmie says that there currently is a 77&amp;quot; base with 230&amp;quot; to date of snowfall. 4&amp;quot; in last 48 hours. That&#39;s impressive 👏 for March!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WA DOT is a bit more conservative.  But our base has grown,  not shrunk in March. They record 53&amp;quot; of new snowfall in last two weeks going from a 55&amp;quot; base to a more healthy 72&amp;quot; base. That is 6 feet of compacted snow. Backcountry skiing should extend well into April once the Avalanche Warning ⚠️ subsides. The Mt. Catherine Loop will be beautiful then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you skiing still, you know that a chance of rain at the Pass has meant snow or patchy clouds at Crystal Springs. The grooming is excellent early in the day but gets chewed up later in the day by lots of skiers on the weekends and the sun if it comes out on the Weekdays. So the best skiing window is just after the groomer comes through around 8am until about noon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are done skiing until next season please hot wax your skis and leave the wax on all Summer to protect your bases. Condition your fixed skins if you have them on your classic skis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you wish to work on technique here&#39;s my last open slots for a private 75 minute lesson this season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday. 8am either skate or Classic
Wednesday 8am and 11am Skate is best
Thursday 8am and 9:30 Classic is option
Friday 9:30 and 11am Skate is best
Sunday 8am skate only
31st 8am and 11am either&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My website Schreckski.com
has all the information if you forgot. $110 for 75 minutes.  Add a friend for just $50 more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reserve, your Venmo payment can link below to my account.  In the notes, list skate or Classic, date and time. Please choose &amp;quot;friends &amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://venmo.com/code?user_id=3339712957775872804&amp;amp;created=1742741311&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you skiing or biking soon! I will be leading Roslyn Gravel Riders Saturday gravel bike rides starting in April.  Let me know if you&#39;re interested.  We start out doing shorter flatter rides in April to stay below the snow line and to adjust to the saddle. We have a &amp;quot;no drop&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;stop for snacks&amp;quot; policy. Usually wheels up at the Rise Roslyn Bike Shop at 9 am on Saturdays.  If you want to ride with me on any other day of the week, my cellphone number is 425 802 6699.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s XC Ski until we bike!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Merry Christmas</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/12/merry-christmas/" />
    <updated>2024-12-18T19:56:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/12/merry-christmas/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas and a happy New XC SKI Year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;It&#39;s looking a lot like Christmas!&amp;quot; up here in the Snoqualmie Pass Corridor.  We should be skiing right after Christmas. I want to thank all of you for choosing me, Schreck, to teach you. 🙏&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which, if you have a family member interested in learning or just trying out XC classic skiing with a lesson or you have a spouse who is an expert XC skate skier who might like a tune-up lesson, you can certainly be Kris Kringle and gift them a lesson or more.  Just let me know what you want the gift lesson to be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A single private lesson for 75 minutes is $110 for one person.  Or you can join them for $160 total.
If they have been good, a two hour private lesson for one is $160. For two skiers, it&#39;s $210.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can include a ski hat (or maybe new boots!) and they can choose their preferred day of the week after they open your card on Christmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Merry Christmas 🎅 🎄 from Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s bike now that we can&#39;t XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Your first upcoming XC ski lesson is just around the corner and there&#39;s snow up at the Pass!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/11/first-upcoming/" />
    <updated>2024-11-12T19:48:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/11/first-upcoming/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi returning and new students,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For returning students,  you know the drill. The more I know about your ski goals, ski strengths, your talents from other sports and how you like to learn, the better it will help me create a positive impact for you on your next ski lesson with me.  And we will build on that first lesson for your next lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For new students,  I ask that you trust that I can help you like I have for all my other students in this, my 12th season teaching full-time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My goal is to teach you the way you want to be taught, to help you love the winter outdoors especially on your XC skis!  So even for my returning students and especially for the lucky few, new to me, beginning/intermediate skiers, answering these questions will help me prepare for your private or duo lessons,  especially the first one of the season.  Just reply back and fill in the blanks below before our first session. Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preferred Name (mine&#39;s Schreck!):
They/she/he:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now  tell me a little about your experience skiing; both Skate/Classic Skiing and/or Alpine/Downhill/BC, that would help me prepare for your first lesson of the season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many years have you Classic/Skate skied?:
How many times a year on average?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;ve taken Classic/Skate XC ski lessons before, where and how long?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If yes, What was easy for you to do on skis?:
What was hard for you to do on skis?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is your favorite sport or activity when you can&#39;t XC ski?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, If you know how you learn best, that helps me emphasize THIS during your lesson and my instruction; so do you learn best listening (auditory learner), seeing (visual) or doing while observing (kinesthetic.)?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any injuries I need to be aware of?:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;You can reply on this questionnaire!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, before your lessons, you can get outside to work on your balance,  cardio, and especially your core. If not, there&#39;s lots of indoor activities that help. Getting on snow is a bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some ideas:
Watch my YouTube videos.  There&#39;s a link to all of the instructional videos for both Classic and Skate technique on my website Schreckski.com.&lt;br&gt;
Try watching a topic that interests you on a bigger screen while you &amp;quot;ski&amp;quot; in your socks in your home.  Work especially on going from one &amp;quot;ski sock&amp;quot; to the other.  If you feel foolish, get your friend or family to join you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your core is your key to proper form. All your ski muscles attach to this strong &amp;quot;box&amp;quot;: 💪 🦵and your upper back muscles.  A weak core makes it hard to execute the fundamental movements.  So some excellent exercises are any core crunch, core stiffen,  lower back and oblique muscles on your sides.  If you can feel the &amp;quot;top of the box&amp;quot;, your diaphragm and your &amp;quot;bottom of the box&amp;quot;, your pelvic girdle/pelvic diaphragm,  you are getting prepared!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, If this all too much for your busy schedule then promise me you will do just this one thing that takes no additional time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you brush your teeth and when you dry yourself off after your shower, do both moving from one foot, balance briefly and then move to the other foot. Trust me, it will help your balance and you will ski so much better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s run, bike, Rollerski, ski bounding, SUP, and work that core until we can XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Early opportunity to Ski!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/09/early-opportunity/" />
    <updated>2024-09-25T14:38:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/09/early-opportunity/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most often asked question I get is when can I start skiing? Well it was just announced this morning that the Methow Valley Ski Camp (MVSC) sign up dates are in about a week!  (See below for sign up details from them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who are interested here&#39;s the details on the Ski Camp. This will be my 4 year teaching.  Before I was an instructor (13 years ago), I loved going to this camp!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my take on the MVSC:
Three full days of on snow group XC ski lessons with an experienced PSIA XC (Professional Ski Instructors of America Cross Country) certified instructor (maybe me!) at Sun Mountain Lodge.  Ski in/ski out, great breakfasts and lunch included at the Lodge. On your own for dinner and lodging.  Small groups of 6-8 self selected skiers of similar abilities and energy levels and your instructor ski out all morning and afternoon with a long lunch break. Warning,  there will be drills but you will learn the PSIA fundamentals from one of the 24 great instructors and be ready for a great XC ski season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, there&#39;s Group Stretching, interesting evening talks on our sport, or just hang out in the pool size jacuzzi or the bar at the lodge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One benefit at Camp is the Swix National Sales Rep, Jack, sets up the pool 🎱 room into a huge waxing room.  He sets out the right waxes for the conditions that day, has all the tools and resources you need to hot wax your skis. There&#39;s someone to help you if it&#39;s your first time working with a ski iron!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, all major XC brands (Fischer, Salomon, Atomic, Madshus, and Rossignol,)  are usually there for you to demo the latest, newest skis and boots. It&#39;s a great way to find the perfect fit in boots and see which ski feels right for you! The local Winthrop Mountain Sports carries a huge selection of everything you need for cross country skiing and they give a good discount during that weekend to campers (MVSC skiers). Please tell them Schreck sent you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&#39;s a chance to meet and have fun with a lot of very excited skiers and instructors. I hope to see you there!
Schedule:
Dates for MVS Camp are December 19th-22nd:
Thursday afternoon,  registration (lots of us also get there early to ski the fresh grooming)
Friday: All day lessons, usually skate. If you&#39;ve never skated, there&#39;s a beginner class on a very nice beginner area! The ski shop at the lodge can rent you everything you need.  Get your gear on Thursday.
Saturday: All day lessons, usually Classic.  If you only skate, there&#39;s a group for &amp;quot;only skaters&amp;quot;.
Sunday: All day ski with your favorite instructor. Skate and Classic classes are offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the dates to register. Remember, it sells out on the second date, sometimes in an hour. So either join their group to leisure sign up on the first day or be quick when registration opens on the second morning.  You were warned!  Here&#39;s their email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ski Camp!
Our oh so popular Ski camp opens registration on October 7th to members, and October 8 for everyone else. As you may know, this fills extremely quickly, so join or renew your membership today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://methowvalleynordic.us3.list-manage.com/track/click?u=62bfe9ee0aac9031ce759a139&amp;amp;id=a1642d6007&amp;amp;e=e3c0df79a8&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;‐---------------------------&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, my website Schreckski.com  is updated for this season and has everything you need if you want to reserve your Skate or Classic XC ski lessons in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on NOAA winter forecast, I am also optimistic we may ski in mid/late  December.  If groomed, here&#39;s the dates open for an early private lesson or two with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;December open dates:
14th,  15th,  16th
23rd
26th,  27th,  28th
29th, 30th,  31st&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January is filling up fast so if you need specific dates or  day of the week, then now is a good time to reserve your preferred slot. As always, sign up for three XC ski lessons and the 4th lesson is on me.  Note that all private lessons are either 75 minutes (25% longer) or two hours. Your choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s bike now that we can&#39;t XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Only 90 days until XC ski season!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/09/90-days/" />
    <updated>2024-09-10T21:11:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/09/90-days/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems a ways off but before you know it, we&#39;ll be XC skiing again.  I can&#39;t wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now is a good time to prepare for an epic season.  The long term weather forecasters are predicting a strong La Nińa after our El Nino last season.  That means a greater chance for colder temperatures and more snow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s my to do list to prepare for another great season of XC skiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure all my skis have their summer wax on. Maybe give them a hotbox treatment while the wax is still on.  This preserves the bases and protects them until it&#39;s ski time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up my cardio. XC skiing puts a big demand on your cardiovascular system; and you are at altitude skiing fast. While you could wait to get in shape on the ski tracks, the weather is perfect to get in some longer sessions on the rollerskis (or skates, blades,etc.),  bikes or running trails (add poles and bound for a more ski specific workout up hills.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My arms are looking even  skinnier than usual! So time for some upper body workouts on the chin-up pole and pull downs with the rubber bands. If you&#39;re like me and have been biking (or running) all off season since April,  you want to start with a strong upper body for all your great poling technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to work the core. More than just sit-ups,  I think of all exercises that strengthen all sides of my core box where all my moving muscles are connected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am planning my early ski vacation to Mt. Bachelor in late November and the Methow Valley in early December.  I will be teaching for the fourth time at the Methow Valley Ski Camp.  It is moved even later to the last long weekend before Christmas: December 19th to Sunday the 22nd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally I plan continuing my education with PSIA (Professional Ski Instructors of America) Instructors courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a tune-up lesson or two, my website: Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is up and updated for this season.  After experimenting last March, I increased private lessons by 25% to 75 minutes. Group lessons are now two hours for better quality of your XC ski lessons. Because I sold out my weekends before the skiing even started last season, if you need a weekend time-slot,  now is a good time to make your request. In the event that two individuals want the same time and date, Venmo receipt reserves it. Please note the new days for each SnoPark. Hyak is for beginning skiers.   Crystal Springs is for intermediate to advanced XC skiers.  As always,  if you purchase 3 weeks of lessons, the 4th lesson is on me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s bike now that we can&#39;t XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thank you for your support!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/04/thank-you/" />
    <updated>2024-04-01T17:12:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/04/thank-you/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski is a small family business; but it&#39;s not just me.  As the 23/24 season comes to a close, I want to thank You!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frances and Annie, help me with all my marketing and social media.  The Realm of Schreckski map (first header on my website), business cards, stickers, etc., are all from them!  Thanks to my kids!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philip White is not only a gifted ski instructor, he spent literally hours into the night helping me improve and build a better website Schreckski.com, for next season.  Thanks again Philip!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski.com is up and ready to go, BTW.  We added links to about 20 YouTube Channel teaching videos so you have something to review while you practice in your wool socks on the wood floors with your Schreckski land drills!  And When I ski with my videography team (that would be Annie Schreck) at Mt. Bachelor in April,  I will post more so please subscribe Schreckski to see them! Comments are appreciated too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly teach students like you in private or couples lessons. December was a difficult month. If it wasn&#39;t for 4 brave students on very thin snow at Hyak and the 21 students on thinner snow in the Methow Valley Ski Camp, I wouldn&#39;t have had 46 student lessons!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;January started slow.  No grooming the first week then bam! Two feet of snow and the season with solid grooming took place. I taught 28 students in 31 lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February was unique in that only 4&amp;quot; of snow fell all month until a foot fell at the end of February! Because of leap year,  I taught 33 students for 54 lessons.  Not too shabby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had our best March with the &amp;quot;25% longer March Madness lessons&amp;quot;.  This was my busiest March by far; 36 students took 53 (25% longer) lessons just in March!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my math is correct, that&#39;s about 122 students taking 184 lessons this season. It is less than our last 22/23 El Nino season, but pretty good considering the poor December and early January snow conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to explain some changes to my scheduling lessons for next season. I experimented with 25% longer lessons in March. Here&#39;s the feedback:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one or two students, four 75 minute lessons are better to learn/improve your XC Skiing experience.  That&#39;s 5 hours in four sessions for the price of three. I increased the time more than the price per hour for next year because I want my students to have enough teaching over 4 lessons to really improve their ability and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one tune-up lesson and for groups of two or three skiers, two hours worked best. Same deal: prepay for three lessons and get the fourth on me. This gives you the best price/hour ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grooming starts earlier now and conditions are best early.  So I moved up all start times 1/2 hour. The early skier gets best grooming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With only 15 minutes between lessons, I cannot race down to the car to change skis and back to the meet-up area in time at Crystal Springs SnoPark. I can at Hyak.  So note what days I teach Skate and Classic XC lessons.  Also, beginning skiers have best experience at Hyak.  Crystal Springs is for intermediate and advanced skiers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunday is now my weekend day to teach those who cannot attend on weekdays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I want to personally thank YOU for skiing with me and helping me be a better ski instructor.  Even after 12 ski seasons, I need help and I work with you to learn what works best for all my ski students. If you could drop me a line with constructive criticism and feedback, that would be great! I will incorporate your advice for the 2024/25 XC season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s bike now that we can&#39;t XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)
Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you come to a fork in the road, take the one less traveled!&amp;quot;
----Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The question I am getting as the snow season winds down and the &quot;off skis on snow season&quot; looms ahead</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/03/winds-down/" />
    <updated>2024-03-19T16:34:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/03/winds-down/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Happy XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s all peaches and cream, skiing on groomed snow; until April Fools Day rolls around here in Washington, and there&#39;s no more grooming for our beloved sport. How do you keep your hard earned ski legs? Your ski fitness? Your balance on one ski skill?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally spend a good part of April XC skiing at Mt Bachelor Nordic Center (6,000&#39; elevation so lots of snow).  They have a Spring Pass: April 1st to about June usually. But I do need to get in gravel racing shape so only skiing in the mornings.  Afternoon is for gravel biking, my other ❤️ 😍&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No worries, you don&#39;t have to travel or buy expensive rollerskis (that&#39;s another Schreckski newsletter.) You don&#39;t need to join a gym (although if you already have, then use it with these drills below!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are serious about this,  a few things can turn your hallway like mine. It&#39;s inexpensive and easy to use because you see it every time you walk down the Hall!
My setup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A chin up bar. Crucial for your double pole and skate poling technique.  If it has multiple positions and elbow straps, so much more fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two pull down rubber cords with ski pole handles. Mimics XC double poling, diagonal poling, V2, V1, V2A etc. Text if you have any questions or want to see my setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A balance ball. Mine&#39;s a Bosu 1/2 ball. Text me for photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A plank board. Mine is Stealth and has games on an App to keep you occupied and motivated to keep on it! See photos by texting me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barbells. Mine can adjust as I get stronger or weaker. Not a crucial feature though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A wall to do chair sits, forward leans, etc. It&#39;s free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get outside and have fun doing what you most like to do! Hike with longish trekking poles; ski bounding is a more vigorous way to add cardio and balance, especially uphill on trails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike, run, SUP, kayak, row, Rollerblade, rollerskate, etc., whatever you love to do!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself recreating near Roslyn, just text me and we can gravel bike, Rollerski, or ski bound!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Saturday is your Funday Ski Day!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2024/03/saturday-funday/" />
    <updated>2024-03-15T13:13:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2024/03/saturday-funday/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a week of incredible XC skiing up here! New snow, cold nights, bluebird days. Perfect Spring Skiing. Bring your sunglasses 🌞 🕶 😎&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOAA Saturday Snoqualmie Pass forecast: 36° F low going to a high of 55! No Wind, Bluebird skies for your skis!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the great bluebird skiing conditions, this brings a lot more skiers than usual for March so plan accordingly 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Crystal Springs SnoPark,  we meet up at the intersection of the P2C Trail and The Stampede Pass Trail going up from our Lot #1, Non-motorized:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;March 16th Saturday Crystal Springs Sno Park:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8:30: Christina, 2nd skate lesson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10:00 am: Marissa and husband,  2nd Skate Lesson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11:30: Vita, 8th Classic lesson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1:30:  Philip, Tatiana etc., Skate up top at Summit East&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to seeing you!
My cellphone number is [...] if you have any questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let&#39;s XC SKI if we can&#39;t bike!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck (Mike)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>