<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Schreck&#39;s cross-country ski news</title>
  <subtitle>News from the waxing bench</subtitle>
  <link href="https://schreckski.com/feed.atom" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://schreckski.com/" />
  <updated>2022-12-07T14:35:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://schreckski.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Schreck</name>
    <email>schreckski@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>How does one prepare for a great day XC skiing?</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/prepare/" />
    <updated>2022-12-07T14:35:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/prepare/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you Jennifer for asking this question about what to prepare before your first XC ski lessons with me and comingupto the Pass to XC ski for the first time.  I thought I&#39;d share it with my students:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things to do before coming up:
Important for safety/$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find/Get your skis out BEFORE the days of your lesson, not the morning of. Trust me, you&#39;ll thank me later.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My students Skiers are often late for their lesson because:
A., there is a long line at the rental counter which doesn&#39;t open early so EVERY renting SKIER is standing around when they do or:
B., &amp;quot;Honey, where did we stash our skis, boots and poles, socks, coats, etc. Last winter?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So:
A. I need to rent:  REI is the best for reserving skis, boots and poles if you live on the West (wet) side of the Pass.  Suncadia rents if you live on the Sunny East Side (have new equipment but only Classic.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.  If you have your own skis, wax them for the conditions! (Hint, waxless skis doesn&#39;t mean you don&#39;t glide wax the tips and tails of your &amp;quot;waxless skis&amp;quot;.  Waxless only means you have scales in your hard wax pocket which still needs a liquid wax to not ice up!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW, I am a wax technician and can hot wax, hot box, structure, and get that white film off your skis. I  do a professional by hand ski tune using the best Swix wax for our type of snow at the Pass. If you&#39;re going to the Methow Valley to XC ski, I have colder waxes as well. Give me your skis after your first lesson and I will lovingly wax them in my shop and return for your next lesson! I charge same as REI, $25 so you save two trips schlepping them there and trust me, I do a much better more meticulous professional job on your precious skis. Hot waxing should last 50 to 100 km of skiing unless you decide to ski in the parking lot to/from your car (please don&#39;t do this!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you need help purchasing new equipment, ask me. Be very careful with used equipment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get your Sno Park Pass for your vehicle. Day pass if you think you&#39;ll only come up a few times. $25 last year. Go online or REI sells daily passes.
If you get the the season pass, get the &amp;quot;special grooming permit&amp;quot; as well, $120 total. Go online or a USF office. Big fine if you don&#39;t get both!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the Weather (for the Pass not Bellevue!) and see the DOT Snoqualmie Pass report.  If they require chains except for all wheel  drive, bring your own as it&#39;s a big fine and expensive to purchase up here. ALSO dangerous to drive up here in your Prius with hard summer tires when traction tires are advised let alone required!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helpful to improve your ski day experience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can warm up and practice some before the lesson,  that would be great. Get there early the day of and/or try to ski the Saturday before.
Try to get your gear on (on the groomed ski trail not the parking lot!) and go play on the flat areas of Trollhaugen if at Crystal Springs SnoPark.  Walk up and down any hills if you are new to skiiing for safety reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most new to cross country skiing skiers dress TOO warmly. Don&#39;t dress like you&#39;re sitting on a chairlift going downhill skiing.  Dress warm just like you&#39;re running or hiking in the winter based on that weather report you checked right?  (See A.3.).  You&#39;ll thank me later in the lesson!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bring a thermos of your favorite warm beverage and good energy foods for afterward. Tailgating after skiing is a fun picnic and it&#39;s a thing that&#39;s fun to do! You will thank me again! No food up here.
Drubrew has refreshments near the West ski area if you forgot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When teaching or free XC Skiing, I bring a small pack with electrolytes/energy fluid and a snack.  + A Buff cuz you can use it so many ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are Sanicans. Use before lesson as only ones are at the Sno Park lot where you are parking. Hyak are warm with indoor plumbing.  Crystal Springs are cold portable potties.  Dress accordingly!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do I CHOOSE XC equipment in the Seattle Metro area?</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/choose-equipment/" />
    <updated>2022-12-03T14:47:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/choose-equipment/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are buying or even renting XC skis this season, this may help you choose the right equipment.  I wrote this for a new to skate skiing skier so pretty basic and skip if you are looking for more racing type equipment ( You should make a pilgrimage to the Mecca for North American XC,  the Methow Valley and Winthrop Mountain Sports.). Thanks Janene for your question and the others who asked for equipment advice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get down to the main REI before they sell out of skis and boots. You could buy online but best to try on boots as each company uses a different last. Some higher volume, some narrower, all built for a European athlete.  Skis and bindings can be bought online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thoughts from working in a ski shop and the Summit Rental Shop helping thousands of skiers find their Cinderella fit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SKATE BOOTS
If you can, pay more for quality boots that fit. You&#39;re feet will thank you as they are the most important part of your equipment for you to have a fun time skate skiing! They are your direct connection to your skis and you want that connection to be solid not sloppy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think snug hiking boot with a very stiff sole. When you flex forward at the ankles, your toes should not touch the front of the boot. Your heel should be snug. No painful spots. Try changing the insoles and ask to be fitted by someone who is an expert on XC boot fitting,  not snowboarding!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t buy a &amp;quot;Combi&amp;quot; boot unless you are buying both classic and skate skis and you are on a budget.  Most are Not great for either skate or Classic XC skiers.  (There is a high quality pursuit boot made for racing where the skier has to race both a skate loop and a classic loop.  They change skis and poles but not boots.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want great ankle support.  The stiffer the better side to side with good forward flex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SKATE SKIS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next most important is your skis. Its not needed to spend as much money on skate skis as your boots to enjoy skate skiing.  What is absolutely important is to get the right flex for your total weight.  The skis&#39; flex needs to fit your total weight with all your ski clothes, boots, fanny pack,  etc.  A too soft ski happens when you under report your weight and they give you a 165cm ski when you really needed a stiffer 175 say. No snap, just wallows (over flexes) and no help in the push off. If you have to choose between two overlapping stiffness ranges in two pair of skis that might work for your total weight, choose the stiffer pair of the two. This is especially true for our typical Snoqualmie area Snowpack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also both skis in a pair need to have similar stiffness.  They should have same serial number for a start.  That means at the factory, they found two skis that were close to the same stiffness You&#39;ll thank me later when learn to skate efficiently!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have them flex tested. Two identical looking skis of the same size,  make and model can vary a lot in flex. For example, I like a specific flex (very stiff like I am wearing a backpack, which I don&#39;t!) both for my weight, my ability to snap it with greater than my bodyweight, and the kind of snow typical of the areas I ski.
So early when all the new skis are stock, I find the right stiffness looking at all the pairs at the length of ski I find the best for my aggressive downhill speed style. They are all different and one usually stands out as perfect for me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;POLES
The handle straps need to be comfortable and easy to get into with your ski glove. You can save money here as more money just gets you more carbon and less weight. And carbon can break. I know, I&#39;ve broken a few very expensive race poles! Get alloy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where some REI employees mess up is in sizing XC poles for both skate and Classic ski poles. The current thinking is with your ski boots on looking forward and standing tall, measure to your nose.  If too short, less power, if too long, harder to control.  Most employees size them like Classic and way too short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BINDINGS
If buying new, no problem,  all nnn compatible bindings work with all in track nnn ski boots finally!  Just Watch out for nnnBC, they are incompatible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also,  Beware if you buy used boots or ski bindings.  So many incompatible brands are out there in the used market. I even had a student show up back in those days with brand new skis, bindings and boots purchased at REI that were incompatible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions,  let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intel on the first of December XC SKIING</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/intel/" />
    <updated>2022-12-02T02:20:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/12/intel/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some photos attached of today&#39;s ski track record conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be just as surprised as I am but the FIRST place on our I-90 Corridor with good grooming goes to.....&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suncadia Trails! See photo for proof. I had a wonderful skate and classic sessions today. Blue skies, good base and groomed this morning again after yesterday&#39;s grooming of the big dump of snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its BC skiing up at Cabin Creek.  See photo attached and thanks to Rob for sharing. They will probably just pack it down tomorrow so don&#39;t go! Not sure when they will plow the parking lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Intel on the P2C Trail is the same, big BC skis are needed as it&#39;s been cold blower powder so powder boards are needed to float on top! They may have started cutting downed trees but the Sno Park parking lot is not plowed nor are the Porta potties out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here&#39;s an idea, I can teach you up here in the sunny, colder Suncadia Trails. Go to (for more info):   Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow&#39;s open for lessons, Friday
10, 11:30, and 1:00.
Same for Sunday the 4th at Suncadia (or Cabin Creek if it&#39;s ready to go.)
8:30 and 10 are still available&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday,  December 3rd, I am hoping to teach at Trollhaugen loops and the P2C Trail at Crystal Springs Sno Park
Available times
8:30 &amp;amp; 11:30&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know getting to Suncadia from Seattle is a longer drive, about 15 minutes longer than driving to Cabin Creek. So come up for the weekend You are close to Cabin and you have Suncadia jic!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are lots of less expensive Airbnbs here in Roslyn Ridge but if money is no object, The Inn at Suncadia is ski in ski out. They have a nice ski shop and are renting brand new freshly waxed (you knew I would check!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meantime, keep up the snow dances! They appear to be working well ❄️&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s ski if we can&#39;t bike up here in the mountains,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can you Believe it? 18 inches of new snow yesterday! The Grooming Schedule</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/grooming/" />
    <updated>2022-11-30T15:18:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/grooming/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I&#39;ve been getting lots of questions about the Snoqualmie I-90 corridor grooming schedule for this coming ski season.  As you recall from last year, it&#39;s a fluid answer especially in early season and, if they run low on funds, also in late season.  Always be prepared for any conditions as we are dealing with Mother Nature and the grooming Piston Bullies can break!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I talked with both groomers for both the State Parks: Crystal to Hyak, and Lake Easton and the separate grooming for Cabin Creek and Trollhaugen areas. They are both scheduled to start December 1st as we got about 18 inches in last 24 hours! The first couple days in December could be rough as it takes a few passes and days to firm up the tracks and skate path. I am guessing Saturday, December 3rd should be the first real day to ski. Thursday and Friday could be sketchy. Get these skis Hot Waxed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trollhaugen loops:  W, F, SA, SU.
Crystal to Hyak: M, W, TH, F, SA, SU.
Amabilis: W or Th, Sa
Cabin lower: M W, Th, F, Sa, Su
Lake Easton: M, W, F, Sa, Su
Suncadia trails: Only after each snowstorm. No regular grooming schedule&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a huge improvement from 10 years ago. Only on Tuesdays is there no grooming. Tuesday has been a good day to Classic ski from Crystal Springs Sno Park to Hyak as it has all night to firm up. Even if it doe snow, skiers keep the tracks open by skiing on them. So it can be a great day to Classic ski! (I only teach Classic at Crystal Springs on Tuesdays for this Reason).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second,  I have been asked: &amp;quot;So what should I do if I didn&#39;t start your recommendation to work out in the previous email?&amp;quot;
So let&#39;s start today working on the two areas one needs, our strength and balance on a moving ski, and that can fit into your busy schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wearing your slippiest socks and on a wood or vinyl floor,  mimic the the skate or Classic motions. Slide and briefly balance on each flat ski with correct arm motion. 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, up against the wall in the sit on a chair position.  Good dorsiflection (ankles bent closer to top of your feet).  Dynamic up and down motion, about 10 inches like your skiing. Visualize skiing downhill. 5 minutes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it;  in just 10 minutes a day, you will have better balance on one ski AND more lower body strength to ski better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski.com
if you need a lesson just email your preferred dates 📅&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently available dates
DEC.  Time. Location
1st.       10.     Hyak
6. Classic  10  Crystal
7th.         10:00, 11:30
8th.    8:30,  11:30
9th.    All
10th.  All
12th.     11:30.   Hyak
13th.    Classic 10.   Crystal
14th.     All&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JANUARY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Set up your tuneup lessons at Schreckski.com cuz the Weather for Snoqualmie Pass, WA (Kittitas County) is kicking it!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/weather/" />
    <updated>2022-11-27T18:07:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/weather/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;https://forecast.weather.gov/MapClick.php?lat=47.4187&amp;amp;lon=-121.412&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;259 AM PST Sun Nov 27 2022&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... WINTER STORM WARNING REMAINS IN EFFECT UNTIL 10 AM PST MONDAY...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHAT, Heavy snow expected. Total snow accumulations of 8 to  15 inches above 3000 feet and 2 to 6 inches below 3000 feet.  Winds could gust as high as 45 mph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHERE, East Slopes of the Washington Cascades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHEN, Until 10 AM PST Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IMPACTS, Travel could be very difficult to impossible. The  hazardous conditions could impact the morning commute. Gusty  winds could bring down tree branches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADDITIONAL DETAILS, Snow will create travel issues along  Interstate 90 over Snoqualmie Pass and Highway 12 over White  Pass. Holiday travelers need to make sure vehicles are  equipped for heavy snow which includes carrying traction  devices or tires, shovels, and flashlights. Travelers may also  consider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes it&#39;s snowing up here in the mountains and is supposed to snow all week. This is good news for grooming at our Snoqualmie area Sno Parks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we get enough snow, the State grooming on the P2C Trail from Crystal Springs Sno Park to Hyak SP and Nick&#39;s grooming at Cabin Creek and Trollhaugen should start December 1st and be ready by this coming Weekend! This is a very early start to our ski season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a tune-up or a 4 pack of skate or Classic XC ski lessons for the price of 3 lessons, here are some dates and times available in December with me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec.   Location. Times available
5th.    Hyak SP.   10am 11:30
7th.  Crystal Springs 10am
8th.  Crystal Springs.   8:30 11:30
9th.  Cabin  all 3 times
10.    Crystal Springs All
12th  Hyak SP    10am
19th  Hyak  SP.  All
21st  Crystal Springs All
23rd  Hyak. 10am
24th. Crystal Springs 10am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are heading up to the Methow Valley Ski Camp December 15-18th, I will be teaching up there again this year.  Ask for me for one or more of your ski lessons. I just got back from skiing there for 5 sessions before Thanksgiving.  Great grooming and excellent snowpack for this time of the year! See photos below, and yes, I am the tallest skier! :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Who wants to prepare for their best Cross Country ski Season?</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/prepare/" />
    <updated>2022-11-13T23:48:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/prepare/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The snow is here and grooming is coming soon!
We may have grooming at the Hyak, Crystal Springs and/or Cabin Creek Sno Parks as soon as December 1st.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in a tuneup Skate or Classic ski lesson,  multiple one hour lessons; and having private or two person lessons,  boogie over to my Website Schreckski.com
to get your favorite day and time.  The La Nina forecast looks promising for an early snow season with colder and wetter conditions this winter. I also really appreciate your referring me to your friends and family who are interested in learning to XC ski more efficiently and live our winters!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My cross country skiing daughter asked me earlier what I do to prepare for the XC ski season and any exercises that she could do at her gym.  I thought I would share with you jic you are interested in this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi Annie,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, biking or ski bounding every day, I do a ski workout in my living room every other day. I don&#39;t have a gym in the winter so I do these in my cabin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A ski erg machine is ideal but several thousand dollars and is what you want to recreate for the most important exercise that mimics XC Skiing: Since you have a gym, all you need is one or two Bosu Balls and rubber cords with two handles. You can use the pull down weight machine but straps work just as well because you don&#39;t need heavy tension.
Basically in all the workouts, feel and be skating or double poling. (doing Classic techniques is a little harder but can be added.) Basically just skate, then double pole, then Classic (4 5 min. sessions  of each) with proper arm swing from one Bosu to the other.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no Bosu, then it still can be done. The Bosu ball (or any unstable surface) adds the snow feeling and improves your balance.  Do it for several sets at a pretty high cadence level thinking about dorsiflection: shin close to top of foot just before push off. Rounded back at similar forward angle as your shin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also think about Hips forward, feel like you&#39;re engaging your Glutes. They are your strongest muscles that often are not engaged (Lazy Glutes!)  Feel like you are squeezing a roll of quarters in your butt crack as you utilize all of your leg muscles in each leg.&lt;br&gt;
Remember, Good high hands, elbows outside hands, for push off.  Basically you are skiing, using the same muscles and practicing good form. It has worked for me for the last 10 seasons and I seem to not lose much efficiency in my ski techniques on the first days on snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Squats.  A variety of ways to mimic squats without weights. First, to use the &amp;quot;chair sit against the wall&amp;quot;, modify by practicing good dorsiflection of your shins. Make it dynamic by sliding up and down the wall. Pretend you are downhill skiing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have weights, try dead lifts. Weight bar on your shoulders, pull-ups with a bent over back using lighter weights of course, etc. Always think like you&#39;re using all your leg muscles, Quads, Glutes and Hamstrings. All can be done with any heavy object you have in your home if you don&#39;t have weights. Try squatting down to a low stool and up. If too easy squat one leg at a time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, work on a Strong core!
3. All of the usual core exercises: my favorite as you know are planks on an unstable surface.  They are really good for skiing! Think of your core as all muscles and stabilizers between your pelvic floor (inside your hips) and your diaphragm. It&#39;s a box 📦 where all of your ski muscles attach to. A strong core enables your muscles to work more efficiently!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bar exercises,  pull-ups with hands at all the different positions.  If you&#39;re too tired, add help by using support from one leg. Hang from the bar and pull up your legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work on dynamic balance.  Sure standing on one leg is OK;  but imitating skiing from one leg and then the other with arm swing and good form is going to be much better to mimic skiing on snow. The Bosu ball is your friend! I leave mine in the narrow hallway between my living room and the bathroom.  I jump on it every time I go by it and when I brush my teeth. I do longer sessions every other day.  Just don&#39;t trip on it in the dark!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working these areas every other day can make a huge difference in just 6 weeks. You can do it all in 45 minutes or get real fast between transitions and get it down to about 25 if you&#39;re interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Still round the corner there may wait,
a new road or a secret gate.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://schreckski.com/news/2022/11/prepare/20221112_122433.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Thank you for a great XC ski season!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/04/thank-you/" />
    <updated>2022-04-18T15:05:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/04/thank-you/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for a great season and allowing me to help you ski better this season. I taught over 75 new and beginning skate and classic skiers this season and hopefully you are excited to continue next season in this great winter sport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Rollerskiing, Rollerskating,  Rollerblading or ski bounding season (all with poles) is upon us. If you need help with anything, please let me know. I have a safe flat newly laid asphalt nearby if you need it. I am happy to help if you&#39;re new to Rollerskiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all this new snow and cold weather, 🥶 😩 some have asked me if they can still XC ski in late April or May on snow? There are two local options and one expensive vacation option:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have wider classic skis, the Cold Creek trail and Mt Catherine loop is usually groomed by other skiers with a fairly decent track. 😉 hint, sometimes the groomer heads out to groom! No way to know but we keep checking! I have really enjoyed the loop as lots of snow and great base especially on top. Lots of climbing though 🤔&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Kongsberger Club has been occasionally pulling a classic track groomer behind a snowmobile at Cabin Creek Sno Park on the Viking, Berg and Road trails. Classic only and no way to know when a volunteer will groom (Maybe after a snow storm?) The snow base is excellent.  Don&#39;t be surprised that the first 50 yards is a sh##storm. Walk past it to see better tracks and cleaner snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vacation option:
So the best 7 days a week groomed 54 KM on snow ski option is Mt Bachelor Nordic Center. I know, you&#39;re thinking it&#39;s at least 5 hours away.  The best and closest to skiing lodging is Loge Camps and they are about 25 mi minutesfrom the Nordic Lodge. Tell Schreck sent you and ask for the Spring special price.  Logecamps.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a lesson from them, contact the Mt Bachelor Nordic Center.  If you want to ski tour with me,  I&#39;ll be back April 27th through May 3rd. No charge but if you find my tips helpful, then I appreciate 🙏 your tips!
I just returned from Mt Bachelor.  They received over 45 inches of cold packed pow while I was there and a couple photos from that trip are below for your viewing pleasure! ⛷&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise, remember to keep up your balance drills, get outside as much as possible to rollerski, bike, run, paddle or whatever rocks your boat!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you out skiing next winter! I also hope to have my daughter Annie videotape some more YouTube videos on my next trip to Mt Bachelor.  And you can connect to my channel on YouTube through my Website: Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s bike if we can&#39;t ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not all who wander
are lost.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How can I better balance on one ski when I skate?</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/03/balance/" />
    <updated>2022-03-17T19:06:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/03/balance/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi skate Skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key is to practice your balance on one leg, year round, not just during the too brief XC snow ski season. As we finish up our snow ski season this month, Here are some progression drills to help you improve and then maintain your Skate ski balance for next season:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Land drills
A.  Practice daily while doing your daily rituals: while brushing and flossing,  while drying off after a shower,  while doing dishes and while watching TV.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply shift smoothly in a V2 or free, no poles skate motion, on a bent ankle and knee, from one imaginary flat ski; then relax, next smoothly repeat to the other leg. (Ideally barefoot or in socks on vinyl or wood floors.) A mirror helps. Doing two things at once improves our balance and fits well into our regular routine.
If this gets too easy for you, close your eyes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B.  In your gym, a Bosu and two pulleys or rubber cords with the handles can mimic the poling and weight shifting of skate skiing. Simply do the V2 then V2 Alternate skate motion from the side of the Bosu to the rounded top and skate back to the ground for 25 times.  Repeat on the other side. Pull down in a double pole V2 or V2A motion as you go up and down from the Bosu balance ball. This is my go to drill every Fall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C.  Ski bounding: in a V2 then V2A skate motion with ski poles, bound up a steep trail or grassy hillsides being sure to land in an athletic body position: Leg bent at knee and ankle, body weight centered on your new foot, with a slight forward lean putting body weight on the double poles, looking forward Not at your shoes. I love the steep mountain bike trails I have up the Cle Elum Ridge near my cabin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D.  If you have access and a safe, smooth bike trail, rollerskiing, Rollerskating, or ice skating are awesome balance and technique workouts in the non snow season.  Proper pads and bike helmet and gloves are required.  The trails and new unused roads at Suncadia is my favorite place to rollerski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Skating on snow:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. Start off not moving forward, just doing the V2 motion from one ski to the other; feeling your body balanced on each ski, going smoothly from one ski to the other on a bended ankle and knee (knee over the toe) and your zipper centered on each ski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B. Marathon Skate with and first without poles making sure to shift fully with a slight pause so you glide on a balanced flat ski (in the tracks) and also shift fully onto the push off ski (the ski angled out of the tracks). Try on slight uphills and then on a slight downhill. Repeat this on both legs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. No poles smooth skating. Pretend you&#39;re a long track speed Skater and make sure to land on a bent ankle and knee, shifting completely over your new ski with nose over knee and knee over your new boot toe that is landing on the snow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Pretend you&#39;re in a tunnel that the top would hit your forehead if you skied upright. Ski in an athletic slightly forward leaning position like you&#39;re racing!  Swing the opposite arm toward the new ski tip you&#39;re landing on. Try gliding longer and longer on each ski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;E. Add poles for V2 then V2A technique focusing on swinging the leg forward and towards your zipper line (center of your body).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;F.  Follow a straight grooming line. Land each boot on the line. Next try gliding longer such that the right boot lands on the Left side of the line and the left boot lands on the Right side of the line.  Always try landing on a bent forward ankle and knee so your push off is powered by your biggest muscles: quads, hamstrings and glutes. No tin soldier skiing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;G.  Next, Try gliding longer by increasing the swing length of your poling to have more time to glide and be on one ski.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H.  Finally, Ski behind a better skier and mimic their technique and glide length.  Do this in their warm up or cool down, not when they are trying to go fast!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreckski.com and Schreckski on my YouTube Channel for more information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not all who wander
are lost.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What a start to our XC Skiing season 👏</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2022/01/what-a-start/" />
    <updated>2022-01-22T04:39:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2022/01/what-a-start/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi fellow XC skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you are enjoying Winter skate skiing and/or Classic skiing this season! After so much snow (too much for DOT and for grooming) in the first week of January, the ski base is the best I&#39;ve ever seen (started skiing here in 92.) Certainly for this early and we should have a very long ski season into April.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also there is a great base and lots of nice groomed loops at Suncadia.  No charge for parking or skiing, lots of parking and groomed nicely for the weekend! It&#39;s about 20 minutes East of Cabin Creek Sno Park on I-90.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a sunny blue bird day and we have a rare extended forecast for dry sunny weather 😎 for an entire week! When have you seen that in January? I have some lesson slots available in this time frame if you want to ski with sunglasses on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dates. Times.  Location
23.       10:30.   Suncadia
24.   8:30, 10.  Cabin
25.  10. 11:30 Crystal Sprgs
26. 8:30, 11:30 Cabin
27.  10, 11:30.   Cabin
28.  8:30, 10.     Cabin
29.  Open.    Suncadia
30. Open.    Suncadia
31. Open.    Cabin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I really appreciate you my ski friends, students and fellow Nordic instructors sharing ideas and tips for enjoying cross country skiing and thus Winter.  The most common questions I&#39;ve been getting from my students before during and after our lessons so far this season might be of interest to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why learn to Classic before learning to skate ski?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some days are great to skate. Others, not so much. But EVERYDAY is a great day to Classic ski. First mastering the fundamentals of the easier to learn Classic diagonal stride, double poling and being confident on downhills and sharp turns will make learning to skate much less frustrating and more fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamentals for Classic skiing, such as: ideal body position, weight transfer, gliding on one ski, etc. will transfer over to your Skate skiing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The YouTube video below does a great job showing this (thanks Chris Chu for sharing)
Watch &amp;quot;Thinking about learning to skate on cross country skis? Watch this video first.&amp;quot; on YouTube:
https://youtu.be/f9uxeoemb5Y&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is the ski trail grooming icy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, This is a good day to Classic!
Skating needs daily grooming to be consistently great.  Ski areas that groom less frequently can be frustrating for Skating and still fine for Classic. We are often above 32 degrees most days and the top of the snow tends to soften due to above freezing temperatures and or solar radiation in the day and then freeze at night.  So go where it is groomed early that morning for the best skate experience. For example, Cabin Creek grooms early every day but Tuesday so that is why their trails are usually the best (and most crowded on Weekends!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3a. How often should I wax my skate skis?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short answer, it depends 🤔
If more debris, any older icier snow (like now) and especially in the Spring,  we hot wax more often.  I recommend you go no more than 50 km between hot waxing your skis; 25 km if the snow is dirty (dust, pine needles, etc.) You&#39;ll ski more efficiently,  protect your ski investment and have happier skis! Also if a big change in the temperatures up or down, well there is a different wax for that!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a certified wax technician btw so if you don&#39;t have the equipment or patience to wax your own skis, leave them with me at the end of your lesson and I will bring them back (I promise!) for your next lesson custom waxed for our snow conditions.  You won&#39;t believe the difference!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3b. I have &amp;quot;waxless skis&amp;quot; so I never need to wax right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry but you do want to hot wax your tips and tails as 3a. Above. For fish scales in the center, a liquid wax is best to prevent icing up. For skin skis, there is Mohair cleaner and ski prep to prevent icing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can I ski more efficiently and effortlessly?
By Working on any/all of the big areas below, these will help immensely:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A. Take lessons from a certified Professional Ski Instructors of America.
Pick me! Here&#39;s my website Schreckski.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;B. Practice the fundamentals you learn every time you are on snow. Do the same drills and progressions you learn from your PSIA Certified Nordic instructor over and over until you become proficient and it&#39;s second nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. Between ski trips, do cardio exercise, work on your balance and mimic skiing in your socks on a hardwood floor. Brush your teeth and dry off from showering by skiing from one leg to the other. Close your eyes when it&#39;s too easy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. Watch ski videos.
The link to mine on YouTube is on my website Schreckski.com
Or go to Schreckski on YouTube. If you like them click that button and hit subscribe! (If you don&#39;t then leave me constructive comments so I can fulfill your wishes.)
Once I get my Great video Graphers like Tatiana or Annie back and sunny weather, I&#39;ll post more video lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, Practice doesn&#39;t make perfect, poor practice makes permanent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you out on the snow soon!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not all who wander
are lost.&amp;quot; Some are just XC Skiers&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are you getting ready for XC Skiing? Some dates open to sign up now!</title>
    <link href="https://schreckski.com/news/2021/12/getting-ready/" />
    <updated>2021-12-03T17:08:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://schreckski.com/news/2021/12/getting-ready/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi fellow and curious bikers and skiers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;30° this am at the Schreckski cabin and a hard frost on the roofs with snow in the forecast. As we transition from one season, i.e. the bike season to the snow season,  I hope you are getting psyched to XC ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things you can be doing while we Wait for the ❄ on the I-90 Corridor:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get in your cardio workouts any way you can! I mostly bike with studded snow tires and use poles to ski bound up the Cle Elum Ridge.  Use your Indoor bike trainer, treadmill, ski erg or any other tool that gets your heart pumped up; this will make the transition to snow easier and more efficient. And more fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some balance work is key and can be fitted into a short period of your workout. Bosu balance ball or bounding from one leg to the other, (weights optional) are an important factor in balancing on a flat ski. If you have rollerskis, focus more on the various techniques. Also I recommend you ski/balance from one leg to the other when you dry off and brush your teeth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight or body bearing workouts will help you be strong instead of sore on your first days skiing.  I use pull down straps, chin up bar, and mostly my body weight like chair sits on a wall, push-ups, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our core is the key to effortless XC Skiing. All of your key propulsion muscles in your quads, arms and upper back are connected to your strong stable core. Planks, crunches, arm hangs with knees up will make your base, the core stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepare your skis. Schreckski.com can help if you don&#39;t have or want the waxing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick a date! After 3 lessons, your 4th lesson is on me. A 4 lesson program will make a big difference in your skills and technique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Openings (contingent on grooming) 9, 10, 11 am, Noon
DECEMBER
13th: Cabin Creek
14th: Crystal Springs
15th:Cabin Creek
16 through 19th: I&#39;ll be teaching at the Methow Valley Ski Instruction at Sun Mountain Lodge.
20th: Cabin Creek
21st:Crystal Springs
22nd: Cabin Creek
23rd: Cabin Creek
24th to 31st I&#39;ll be skiing down South with my kids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let&#39;s Bike until we ski!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schreck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Not all who wander
are lost.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>